National Rifles 051
People's Archive, MLK Library
National Rifles Scrapbook Collection
1880-1889
People's Archive, MLK Library
District of Columbia. Militia. National Rifles
051
5 Boxes
Biographical / Historical
The National Rifles, an independent company of the D.C. Militia, was organized in 1859 in the wake of John Brown's raid. It was the first company of citizen troops ordered into the Civil War in 1861. A few years after the War, the militia disbanded or merged with other troops. The National Rifle Armory was located on G Street NW between 9th and 10th at the site of the current Mather Building, directly across from the Martin Luther King Jr. Memorial Library. Members of the company formed a veteran's organization to hold annual reunions, fairs, soirees, dinners, and other events to commemorate the anniversary of their founding and military service.
Custodial History
The Scrapbooks were donated to the Library in 1929 by Mr. and Mrs. Evans.
Scope and Contents
The scrapbooks contain clippings, invitations, programs, memorabilia, handwritten and typewritten letters, ledgers, receipts, meetings minutes, and a few copies of Canteen, the daily record of the National Rifles and an oversized poster for the July 4th Military Celebration in St. Louis, Missouri. Also included is a box of cabinet card images of uniformed members of the National Rifles. Notes on the back of the photographs indicate that the images came from the Evans Collection in November 1929.
Arrangement
Armed Forces; District of Columbia. Militia; Scrapbooks; Ephemera; Organizational Records; Correspondence; Photographs; Pennsylvania Quarter (Washington, D.C.); Veterans
- Series 1
  - Scrapbook, 1880-1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Rifles Fair Scrapbook, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1885-1895 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1895-1899 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Acker, G. N., Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Barksdale, William H., Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Blois, J. F. H., Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Boteler, W. P., Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bowers, H. C., Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Brooks, Charles W., Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Burkart, Frank A., Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Burkart, Frederick W., Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Burnside, J. O. P., Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Choate, Warren R., Jr., Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Clear, James H., Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Colladay, W., Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Constant, Robert E., Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Ellis, W. K., Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fonda, Charles B., Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Fox, James C., Undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Garner, T. A., Undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Geneste, Leon D., Undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Green, A. J., 1893 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Holmes, Lewis, Undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Howell, J. W., Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Keech, W. C., Undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Moore, Robert E., Undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Oyster, J. F., Undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Paige, C. H., 1882 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Paige, C. H., Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Sayles, Arthur U., Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Simms, C. E., Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Simms, C. E., Undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Stokes, George W., Undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Stone, O. P. D., 1881 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Taylor, C. McC., 1889 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Taylor, George W., Undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Unknown, Undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Warner, C. H., Undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Williams, Sherman, Undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Woodley, Will T., Undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Zantizinger, D., 1881 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Oversized folder, Undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Poster for July 4th military celebrations in St. Louis, Undated (Box 5, Folder 40)